Guide to the Hart Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Hart family papers
1721-1894
1721-1850
MS 265
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Principally the papers of the related Hart and Norton families of Connecticut, descendants of Hawkins Hart. Included are correspondence, legal papers, chiefly concerning the transfer of property in Wallingford, Barkhamsted, Farmington and Berlin, and writings on religious topics. The correspondence consists of letters of the Norton family of Berlin, Connecticut written mostly between 1835 and 1846 to their son, William H. Norton, who was living in Troy, New York and then in Georgia. The letters discuss slavery, religion, family finances, and also describe the death of a daughter of the family in 1839. Also mentioned in the papers are the Hooker, Cowles and Brownson families.
Hart family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Walter E. Crittenden, 1940; additional papers purchased in 1947.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
These papers of the inter-related Hart and Norton families of Connecticut include correspondence, legal and financial papers dealing with estates and land holdings in Connecticut, and miscellaneous writings and other papers.
The bulk of the papers are deeds, writs, and other estate papers belonging to several branches of the Hart and Norton families, 1721-1876. They include deeds and indentures for land in Wallingford and Barkhamsted belonging to Hawkins Hart (1736-1824) and his descendants and estate papers of Hawkins Hart, Jr. (1781-1836), and deeds of properties in Farmington and Berlin belonging to Isaac Hart (b. 1686), his descendants, and members of the Norton family of Berlin. Also mentioned are members of the Hooker, Cowles, and Brownson families.
The correspondence consists of approximately forty-five letters of the Norton family of Berlin, being for the most part letters written to William H. Norton, who lived in Georgia and Troy, New York, from his parents, Albert (d. 1847) and Lucy (Hart) Norton, and his brother Albert R. Norton. The letters, written between 1819 and 1885, describe family financial matters and events such as the death of Harriet Norton (1839 Sep 8), while the letters of Albert Norton in particular express antislavery sentiments and strong religious beliefs.
Other miscellaneous items in the collection include a catalogue of members of the family of Solomon Dunham, a roll of the Kensington, Connecticut, militia, and writings on religious topics, including a printed copy of a sermon preached by Royal Robbins at the funeral of Ruth Hart.
The papers of the Hart and Norton families of Farmington and Berlin were placed in Yale University Library by Mrs. Walter E. Crittenden in 1940. The remaining papers were purchased from Dawson's Book Shop in 1947.
Death; Families; Slavery -- United States; Barkhamsted (Conn.); Berlin (Conn.); Connecticut; Farmington (Conn.); New York (State); Southern States; United States -- Religion; Wallingford (Conn.); Deeds; Wills; Hart, Hawkins, 1736-1824; Hart, Hawkins, 1781-1836; Hart, Selah, 1732-1806; Norton, Albert, d. ca. 1847; Norton, Lucy Hart; Branson family; Cowles family; Hart family; Hook family; Norton family
- Inventory
  - Hart and Norton families of Farmington and Berlin, Connecticut
    - "A Catalogue of the Family of Solomon Dunham from Thursday March 2d 1758", [post-1853] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Roll of militia in Kensington [part of Berlin, Connecticut]", [1812-1815?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Norton family: correspondence [Albert and Lucy (Hart) Norton; their children, Albert R., William H., Lucy H., and Harriet; and a few of their Hart relations. Between 1835 and 1846, when most of the letters were written, the parents and daughters were living in Berlin, Albert R. was living there and in Troy, New York, and William H. was living in Troy and in various places in Georgia.], 1819-1820, 1835-1846, 1855, 1885-1886, undated (Box 1, Folder 2 - 7)
    - Hart family (including Selah Hart) and Norton family (principally Roger Norton, Roger Norton, Jr., and Albert Norton): legal and financial papers
      - Farmington deeds, 1721-1782 (Box 1, Folder 8 - 11)
      - Berlin
        - Deeds, 1786-1831, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 12 - 14)
        - Estate papers, 1803-1806, 1825-1838 (Box 1, Folder 15 - 17)
        - Miscellaneous papers, 1844-1850 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Religious papers
      - "Questions for discussion at Maternal meetings", 1837 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Royal Robbins: The Happiness of a Long and Useful Life..., 1844 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Poems and notes, 1894, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Hart family of Wallingford and Barkhamsted, Connecticut
    - Hawkins Hart (1736-1824) of Wallingford: deeds, 1760-1791 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Hawkins Hart, Jr. (1781-1836) of Barkhamsted, Connecticut: deeds, writs, estate papers, 1808-1809, 1826-1838 (Box 1, Folder 21 - 22)
    - William Henry Harrison Hart (1812-1864) of Barkhamsted, Connecticut: deeds, 1838-1842 (Box 1, Folder 22)